{"tossups": [{}, {"question": "Pittsburgh Pirates player Roberto Clemente died in an airplane accident en route to this nation. As a filibuster, William Walker overthrew this country\u2019s government. Violeta Chamorro led this nation in the 1990s, ending a war in which one side was controversially supported by Ronald Reagan\u2019s administration. Sandinista leader Daniel Ortega currently leads, for ten points, what Central American nation with capital Managua?", "answer": "<b> Nicaragua</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During one campaign, this man\u2019s running mate asked \u201cWho am I? Why am I here?\u201d in a debate\u2019s opening statement. During that campaign, this man claimed that a \u201cgiant sucking sound\u201d could be heard as NAFTA funneled jobs to Mexico. This founder of Electronic Data Systems spent $60 million on his campaign, but finished third behind George H.W. Bush and Bill Clinton. For ten points, name this Texan billionaire who ran as an independent in the 1992 Presidential election.", "answer": "Henry Ross<b> Perot</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Donald McCraig authored a 2007 sequel to this novel about one of its central characters\u2019 exile from Charleston. A confrontation on a staircase in this novel leads to its pregnant protagonist breaking her ribs. This novel ends with the protagonist optimistically stating that \u201ctomorrow is another day\u201d. For ten points, name this Margaret Mitchell novel set in Civil War-era Georgia, whose 1939 film adaptation starred Vivien Leigh as Scarlett O\u2019Hara and is the inflation-adjusted most successful film in box office history.", "answer": "<b> Gone with the Wind</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "Although nobody died because of this accident near Harrisburg, public reaction to it led to the cancellation of over fifty planned reactors. For ten points, name this 1979 incident in which a Pennsylvania nuclear plant went into partial meltdown.", "answer": "<b> Three Mile Island</b> incident (or accident, etc.) Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man gave a series of benefit concerts in response to the Great Fire of Hamburg, and his travels with Countess Marie d\u2019Agoult inspired his Years of Pilgrimage. He included slow \u201classan\u201d and fast \u201cfriska\u201dsections in a set of nineteen works, the fifteenth which was based on the \u201cRakoczi March.\u201d Heinrich Heine coined a term to describe the frenzied reception he received in Berlin. For ten points, name this virtuoso Romantic pianist who wrote the<em> Hungarian Rhapsodies</em> and was the subject of a namesake \u201cmania.\u201d", "answer": "Franz<b> Liszt</b> (or<b> Liszt</b> Ferenc)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man was hired by the Muscovy Company to find a route to Japan and China, but ice fields at Svalbard cut his journey. Members of this man\u2019s crew on the<em> Discovery</em> mutinied and left him with his teenage son on a small boat in a body of water now named for him. For ten points, name this English explorer whose expeditions for the Dutch East India Company paved way for the colonization of New York, where a river is also named for him.", "answer": "Henry<b> Hudson</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "One ruler of this dynasty beheaded Jafar Yahya, leading to the decline of the Barmakid family. That ruler of this dynasty, Harun Al-Rashid, created the House of Wisdom and gave Charlemagne the elephant Abul-Abbas. This dynasty\u2019s capital, Baghdad, was sacked by the Mongols in 1258. For ten points, name this Islamic caliphate that succeeded the Umayyad dynasty.", "answer": "<b> Abbasid</b> Caliphate", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Genoese crossbowmen were hacked down by friendly forces while retreating during this battle, and one commander at this battle adopted the motto and crest of the blind King John of Bohemia, who died at this battle. That commander was refused help by his father in this battle, saying \u201clet the boy win his spurs\u201d; those commanders were Edward the Black Prince and Edward III. The dominance of the longbow was confirmed in, for ten points, what first decisive English victory in the Hundred Years War?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Crecy</b> <b>Second Quarter</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This nation\u2019s motto, \u201cDeo Vindice,\u201d was developed by Thomas Semmes. The Stone Fleet was sunk to blockade this nation, which had two of its diplomats captured in the Trent Affair.<em> Texas v. White</em> rejected the claim that the U.S. was to recognize this nation, whose only Vice President was Alexander Stephens. For ten points, name this country led by Jefferson Davis which seceded from the Union to spark the U.S. Civil War.", "answer": "<b> Confederate States of America</b> (accept the<b> Confederacy</b>, accept<b> C.S.A.</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This nation\u2019s economic ruin in the 1950s led to its genre of \u201cscar\u201d literature. One author from this country described his spiritual journey after learning of his survival from cancer. The protagonist of another novel set in this country was born with a jade piece in his mouth and is destined to marry his cousin despite his true love for another cousin. This country\u2019s Four Great Classical Novels include the <em>Romance of the Three Kingdoms</em> and<em> Water Margin</em>. For ten points, name this country, the birthplace of Nobel laureates Gao Xingjian [sheeng-jee-ahn] and Mo Yan.", "answer": "People\u2019s Republic of<b> China</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "Prince Bagration stalled for time prior to this battle at the Battle of Sch\u00a8ongrabern, and the plan for one side in this battle was created by Franz von Weyrother. The unfortunate General Mack surrendered at the Battle of Ulm prior to this battle, which saw Marshal Soult lead an assault on the Pratzen Heights. Michael Kutusov was demoted prior to this battle by Tsar Alexander I, who, along with Emperor Franz II, was present at this battle. The Third Coalition and the Holy Roman Empire was dissolved after, for ten points, what Battle of the Three Emperors, an 1805 victory for Napol\u00b4eon?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Austerlitz</b> (accept Battle of the<b> Three Emperors</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This state\u2019s second governor, Edward Coles, stood down pro-slavery \u201cEgyptians\u201d from this state\u2019s southern third. Even with protection from this state\u2019s governor, Thomas Ford, Joseph Smith was killed in this state\u2019s town of (+) Carthage. One politician from this state noted \u201cI believe this government cannot endure, permanently, half (*) </b> slave and half free\u201din his \u201cHouse Divided\u201d speech. For ten points, name this state represented in Congress for one term by Abraham Lincoln.", "answer": "<b> Illinois</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Warning: two answers required. One of these two countries was aided by the New Model Army against the other country at the Battle of the Dunes. The Duc d\u2019Enghein switched sides to command the army of one of these countries, which he had earlier defeated at the</b> <b>Battle of (+)</b> <b>Rocroi in the service of the other.</b> <b>One of these countries tried to place</b> <b>One of these countries tried to place</b> <b>Phillip of Anjou on the throne of the other after the death of (*)</b> <b>Phillip of Anjou on the throne of the other after the death of (*)</b> <b>Phillip of Anjou on the throne of the other after the death of (*)</b> Charles II, resulting in a Bourbon alliance. For ten points, the Treaty of the Pyrenees was signed by what two countries, one of whose namesake succession war was started by the other\u2019s Louis XIV.", "answer": "<b> France</b> and<b> Spain</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This group suffered heavy causalities while taking Hamburger Hill during the Vietnam War. Bad weather led to greater than expected casualties for this group during its Mission Albany, the precursor to Operation Neptune. During Operation Market Garden, this group</b> <b>secured (+)</b> <b>\u201cHell\u2019s Highway.\u201d Their commanding officer, Anthony McAuliffe, replied</b> <b>\u201cHell\u2019s Highway.\u201d Their commanding officer, Anthony McAuliffe, replied</b> <b>\u201cHell\u2019s Highway.\u201d Their commanding officer, Anthony McAuliffe, replied</b> <b>\u201cNuts!\u201d when asked to give up (*)</b> <b>\u201cNuts!\u201d when asked to give up (*)</b> Bastogne during the Battle of the Bulge. For ten points, name this American light infantry division, also used by President Eisenhower to desegregate Little Rock Central High School in 1957.", "answer": "<b> 101st Airborne</b> Division (prompt on partial answer)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This artist painted Pitt the Elder collapsing after giving a speech protesting American independence in his</b><em><b> Death of the Earl of Chatham</b></em><b> and painted General George Augustus</b> <b>Elliot on horseback pointing towards burning (+)</b> <b>Spanish ships in</b><em><b> The Siege of Gibraltar</b></em><b>.</b> <b>He painted his half-brother with a pet rodent in (*)</b><em> Boy With a Squirrel</em>, and depicted the rescue of a man who was attacked by the title animal in the Havana Harbor. For ten points, name this 18th century American painter of<em> Watson and the Shark</em>.", "answer": "John Singleton<b> Copley</b> Page 9", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>In this state in 2012, Marissa Alexander fired a \u201cwarning shot\u201d at her estranged husband. An unarmed resident of this state\u2019s city of Sanford was shot by George (+) Zimmerman; in the ensuing trial, the defense did not invoke this state\u2019s 2005 \u201cStand Your Ground\u201d law, as Zimmerman instead claimed self-defense against (*)</b> Trayvon Martin. For ten points, name this state where the Stand Your Ground law was expanded in 2014 by Governor Rick Scott.", "answer": "<b> Florida</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s theory of \u201cconatus\u201d refers to the universal drive that humanity has towards an essential being. He claimed that natural law principles prevented the existence of</b> <b>miracles, and he controversially claimed that Ezra, not (+)</b> <b>Moses, wrote the Torah. He</b> <b>equated Nature with God, helping lead to his exclusion from a community of</b><em><b> conversos</b></em><b>, (*) </b>Jews who had fled the Portuguese Inquisition for Amsterdam. For ten points, name this 17th century Dutch philosopher and author of<em> Ethics</em>.", "answer": "Baruch<b> Spinoza</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b>A friend of this man was beheaded when they attempted to flee his country, possibly to defect to George II of Britain. This monarch created an alliance of German princes called</b> <b>the Furstenbund and oversaw the First (+)</b> <b>Partition of Poland.</b> <b>The death of Empress</b> <b>Elisabeth led this ruler to sign a peace treaty with Peter the Great in a conflict where his army won at Rossbach, which he began by invading Saxony. His Anti-Machiavel influenced (*) </b> Voltaire to correspond with this monarch who also invited J.S. Bach to Potsdam. For ten points, name this leader of Prussia during the Seven Years War.", "answer": "<b> Frederick II</b> of Prussia (<b>Frederick the Great</b> or<b> Frederick IV</b> of Brandenburg)  (1) <b>An attack on Cadwallader Colden\u2019s home was precipitated by news of this</b> <b>legislation, which the \u201c12 Immortal Justices\u201d ruled against in Maryland. The</b> <b>Declaration of Rights and Grievances was written by John Dickinson in a (+)</b> <b>Congress named for this piece of legislation, and Committees of Correspondence were</b> <b>set up to boycott goods as a result of this act. The (*)</b> Declaratory Act was passed on the same day as this legislation\u2019s repeal, which was encouraged by Lord Rockingham. For ten points, name this 1765 Act imposed by the British Parliament on printed materials. ANSWER:<b> Stamp Act</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}